<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The life of the Reverend Anthony Horneck, D.D., late preacher at the Savoy by Richard Lord Bishop of Bath and Wells.</title>
            <author>Kidder, Richard, 1633-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47332</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K407</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31552</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12105226</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12105226</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54145</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47332)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54145)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1013:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The life of the Reverend Anthony Horneck, D.D., late preacher at the Savoy by Richard Lord Bishop of Bath and Wells.</title>
                  <author>Kidder, Richard, 1633-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.H. for B. Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: The life of Dr. Horneck.</note>
                  <note>Errata on p. 62.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Horneck, Anthony, 1641-1697.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54145:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LIFE Of the Reverend <hi>Anthony Horneck,</hi> D. D. Late Preacher at the SAVOY.</p>
            <p>By <hi>RICHARD</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>B. Aylmer</hi> at the Three Pigeons in <hi>Cornhill</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:54145:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:54145:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The <hi>LIFE</hi> of the Reverend <hi>Anthony Horneck</hi> D. D.</head>
            <p>THIS excellent Man was born<note n="*" place="margin">Anno 1641.</note> at <hi>Baccharach</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">So call'd, as ſome think, from <hi>Bacchia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> Pid. <hi>Miſſon</hi>'s Trav. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> Lett. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>, in the <hi>Lower Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate,</hi> a Town from whence we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Wine that from the place bears the ſame Name amongſt us. His Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was <hi>Recorder</hi> or <hi>Secretary</hi> of that place; a very ſtrict Proteſtant, and a Perſon of great Reputation. The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor was alſo bred up in the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion from the beginning: He never was of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as hath been falſly reported of him. His Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther devoted him for the holy Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry from the womb, and was not wanting to give him ſuch an Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as might fit him for that Sacred Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. He was firſt ſent to <hi>Heidelbergh,</hi> where he applied himſelf with great diligence to the ſtudy of Divinity, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the direction and care of the very learned Dr. <hi>Spanheim,</hi> who is now the primary Profeſſor of the Univerſity of <hi>Leyden.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:54145:3"/>
            <p>He had, it appears, a great deſire to come over into <hi>England;</hi> I cannot tell what it was that moved him: 'tis certain his Father inclined not to it. However to <hi>England</hi> he came, not without his Father's conſent. He was about 19 years of age when he firſt came over. He was then very emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent not onely for his Learning, but for his great Piety alſo. He who taught him the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue, does profeſs, that he never ſaw a young man ſo exemplary for Piety as this young man was.</p>
            <p>He was entred into <hi>Queen's College</hi> in <hi>Oxford, Dec.</hi> 24. 1663. and was in very great eſteem there with Dr. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,</hi> then <hi>Provoſt</hi> of that Houſe, and ſince Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> who valued him highly for his great Learning, and more particularly for his good skill in the Eaſtern Languages. He was, by his favour, made Chaplain of the ſaid College ſoon after his Entrance. He was incorporated Maſter of Arts from the Univerſity of <hi>Wittembergh, Dec.</hi> 21. 1663. It was not long after this, that he was made Vicar of <hi>Allhallows</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> which is in the gift of <hi>Lincoln College.</hi> There he continued a moſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54145:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>conſtant and painfull Preacher about two years.</p>
            <p>Thence he removed into the Family of the Duke of <hi>Albemarle</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Au.</hi> 1665.</note>, and was received there as a Tutor to his Son, the then Lord <hi>Torrington,</hi> and ſince Duke of <hi>Albemarle.</hi> He was now in a fair way to Preferment, had he been forward in fecking it. The Duke did indeed beſtow upon him a Living in the Dioceſe of <hi>Exeter</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory of <hi>Doulton</hi> in <hi>Devon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</hi>
               </note>, and did alſo procure him a Prebend in that Church from Dr. <hi>Sparrow,</hi> then Lord Biſhop there, I ſhall have occaſion afterward to give on account of his parting with them. I am now on that part of the Doctors Life which I know the leaſt of; I doubt not but he did well every where, and agreeably to his holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
            <p>He did, before he married, go over into <hi>Germany</hi>
               <note n="|" place="margin">
                  <hi>Au.</hi> 1669.</note>, to ſee his Friends, where he preached with great acceptation, and was entertained with great reſpect at the Court of one of the <hi>German</hi> Princes<note n="*" place="margin">Charles Lodowick <hi>Elector</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine.</note>, who ſhewed him a very particular kindneſs.</p>
            <p>After his Return he was choſen Preacher at the <hi>Savoy</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Au.</hi> 1671.</note>, where he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued about 26 years, till he died.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54145:4"/>That place deſerves not the name of a Preferment: The maintenance is ſmall, and, upon the matter, precarious. And whatever it was to him at his firſt taking of it, when there were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of conſiderable quality inhabiting there, who were very kind to him; yet afterwards, when his Family in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, and his neceſſities were grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it could not be called a compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent maintenance. But whatever it was firſt or laſt, he could not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to keep his Living in <hi>Devonſhire</hi> with it; nor could he ever be prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with afterwards (whatever offers were made to him) to accept of any Living to hold in conjunction with it. He was irreconcileable to <hi>Pluralities,</hi> and to <hi>Non-reſidence,</hi> and would upon occaſion declare his abhorrence of them with ſome conſiderable warmth.</p>
            <p>He was of the opinion, in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, of <hi>Bernard Gilpin,</hi> the famous Preacher and Saint of the North, of whom the Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> who wrote his Life, gives the following ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. <q>Mr. <hi>Gilpin</hi> was about to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel beyond the Seas, and to ſtudy there: He was at that time poſſeſſed of a Living, a Cure of Souls; Biſhop
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54145:4"/>
                  <hi>Tunſtall</hi> perſwades him to keep his Living for his better ſupport; Mr. <hi>Gilpin</hi> refuſeth ſo to doe, and reſigns it. He tells the Biſhop, that <hi>he had left his Parſonage upon neceſſity, becauſe he could not keep it in his hands with any peace of Conſcience.</hi>
               </q> And when the Biſhop offered him a Diſpenſation to hold it, Mr. <hi>Gilpin</hi> replied, <q>
                  <hi>The Devil will not be reſtrained with any bonds of diſpenſation from labouring in mine abſence the deſtruction of my people committed to my charge: And I fear that when God ſhall call me to account of my Stewardſhip, it will not ſerve my turn to make anſwer, that I was diſpenſed withall, whilſt the Devil made havock of my Flock.</hi>
               </q> Mr. <hi>Gilpin</hi> was after this, and whilſt he continued beyond the Seas, preſſed to accept of a Living: But he tells the Biſhop, in his Letter to him, his mind in theſe words: <q>
                  <hi>I am fully reſolved, ſo long as I live, never to burden my Conſcience in this caſe, nor to keep a Living in my own charge with condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to live from it.</hi>
               </q> He adds after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, <q>
                  <hi>Though any other ſhould teach and preach for me as conſtantly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly as even St.</hi> Auguſtin <hi>did,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54145:5"/>yet cannot I think my ſelf diſcharged by another man's pains-taking. But if yet I ſhould be perſwaded thus to offer violence to my Conſcience, upon condition to remain either here, or in any other <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, my diſquiet of Conſcience would never permit me to profit in my ſtudy.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>He was a very great bleſſing to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and indeed to the City. He conſtantly reſided among them, tho' he had no Houſe belonging to his Place. He hired an Houſe, and was conſtant in the diſcharge of the Duties of his Place. He preached with great vehemence and ardor, with mighty force and conviction. He ſpake the ſenſe of his Soul, and entred into the Hearts of his People. He ſoon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced his Auditors that he was in great earneſt, and that he had a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſenſe of the worth of Souls, and of the vaſt importance of thoſe Truths which he delivered to them.</p>
            <p>His Auditors were convinced that he was a Man of God, and ſent by him for the good of Souls. He uſed great freedom of Speech, and inſtead of uſing <hi>enticing Words of human Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> he ſpake like his Maſter with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54145:5"/>great Conviction and Authority.</p>
            <p>His Fame grew exceedingly, and very many were his conſtant Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, ſome of the higheſt Rank and Quality, and a very great number of very devout and pious Perſons. A vaſt Crowd there was that followed him, and ſuch a collection of moſt devout and conformable Perſons as were hardly to be found elſewhere; it was no eaſie matter to get through the Crowd to the Pulpit.</p>
            <p>He adminiſtred the Holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion on the firſt Sunday of every Month, and preached a Preparation. Sermon on the Friday preceding. He did it alſo on the great Feſtivals. He adminiſtred it twice on a day, in the Morning at eight a Clock, and at the uſual time after the Morning Sermon. The number of the Communicants held a great proportion to that of his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, and their Devotion was very exemplary. The number was ſo great at both times, that it will hardly be believed by thoſe Clergymen who have been confined to the Country, and have ſeen the ſmall number of thoſe who attend upon this holy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. So great was the number, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54145:6"/>there was need of great help of Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gymen to aſſiſt in the delivering of the Bread and Wine; and with ſuch aſſiſtance it was very late before the Congregation could be diſmiſſed. I will add, that I do not remember that I did ever behold ſo great numbers, and ſo great ſigns of Devotion, and a due ſenſe and profound reverence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming this great act of divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, in my whole life. The Doctor took indefatigable pains on thoſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, but he was encouraged to do ſo from the great ſucceſs his Labours met withal.</p>
            <p>He was not only very diligent in Preaching and Adminiſtring the Holy Sacrament, but in all other parts of his Duty.</p>
            <p>He took great pains in Catechiſing and inſtructing the Youth, in viſiting the ſick, and directing and ſatisfying the doubtfull and ſcrupulous, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging all good beginnings, and promoting worthy deſigns, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking thoſe he converſed with to love and good works.</p>
            <p>He took great pains alſo in his own Family. He ſpent very much time with his Family in conſtant Prayers
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54145:6"/>Morning and Night, in Reading the Holy Scriptures, Singing of Pſalms, in holy Conferences, and all the Duties incumbent upon him as the Maſter of a Family. No Wearineſs, no weighty Buſineſs abroad, excuſed him from the diſcharge of theſe Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Nor did he perform them ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and perfunctorily, but ſpent very much time in them; he was very aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiduous, very earneſt and vehement, and ſhewed a very great concern and ardor therein. He would riſe early in a Morning to theſe Exerciſes, and not ſpare his pains even after the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great and weariſom labours of the day.</p>
            <p>Nor did he forbear his Studies and Cloſet-Devotions. He ſpent much time there. It appears by a Diary found ſince his Death, and which he kept for a long time, that he called himſelf to an account every Night for the Words, and Actions, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of the Day paſt; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps few men living were more ſtrict and ſevere than he was in this matter. It he had done any good that day, he gave God the praiſe of it before he ſlept And few men that lived paſſed ſewer days
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54145:7"/>(if he paſſed any ſuch) without do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good. But when any Words or Thoughts eſcaped, which he judged to have wanted due care, he animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted upon himſelf in a ſevere man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, before he went to reſt. He was one of the kindeſt men to others that ever lived, and one of the ſevereſt to himſelf. He needed no Confeſſor to call him to account, or to enjoyn him any Penance. He did not ſpare revenge upon himſelf, who could moſt eaſily forgive his Enemies, and wanted no compaſſion for the greateſt Criminals. He kept a continual watch over his own Soul, and ſtrictly watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over its actings, and tendencies, and was therefore very ſit to watch over thoſe who were committed to his Charge.</p>
            <p>Beſides the conſtant care that was upon him from his Pariſh, his Family, his Cloſet and Studies, he imployed himſelf in doing good to thoſe who were more remote. He encouraged Piety where-ever he came, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in the younger ſort. He had the care of ſeveral Societies of Young Men, whom he directed and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged. And becauſe this matter hath
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54145:7"/>been miſ-underſtood, and that to my certain knowledge, there was an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, ſince this Revolution, to black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the Doctor on this account, I ſhall repreſent the matter juſt as it was.</p>
            <p>Certain it is that there were ſome Societies of religious and devour Young Men under the Doctor's Government and Inſpection. But whether the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor did move theſe Young Men at firſt to enter into ſuch Societies, or whether they firſt applied to him, and he only gave them Rules to govern themſelves by, I am not able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine. Thus much is certain, that he gave them Rules, and they were theſe that follow.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That all that entered into ſuch a Society ſhould reſolve upon an holy and ſerious Life.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. <hi>That no perſon ſhall be admitted into this Society till he arrive at the age of Sixteen, and hath been firſt confirmed by the Biſhop, and ſolemnly taken on himſelf his Baptiſmal Vow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>III. <hi>That they chuſe a Miniſter of the Church of</hi> England <hi>to direct them.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:54145:8"/>
               <item>IV. <hi>That they ſhall not be allowed in their meetings to diſcourſe of any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted point of Divinity.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>V. <hi>Neither ſhall they diſcourſe of the Government of Church or State.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VI. <hi>That in their meetings they uſe no Prayers but thoſe of the Church, ſuch as the Litany and Collects, and other preſcribed Prayers; but ſtill they ſhall not uſe any that peculiarly belongs to the Miniſter, as the Abſolution.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VII. <hi>That the Miniſter whom they chuſe ſhall direct what practical Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhall be read at theſe meetings.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VIII. <hi>That they may have liberty, after Prayer and Reading, to ſing a Pſalm.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>IX. <hi>That after all is done, if there be time left, they may diſcourſe each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about their ſpiritual concerns; but this ſhall not be a ſtanding Exerciſe, which any ſhall be obliged to attend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>X. <hi>That one day in the Week be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for this meeting, for ſuch as cannot come on the Lords Day; and that he that abſents himſelf without cauſe ſhall pay three Pence to the Box.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>XI. <hi>Every time they meet, every one ſhall give ſix Pence to the Box.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:54145:8"/>
               <item>XII. <hi>That on a certain day in the year, <hi>viz. Whitſun-Tueſday,</hi> two Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards ſhall be choſen, and a moderate Dinner provided, and a Sermon preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Money diſtributed (neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Charges deducted) to the Poor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>XIII. <hi>A Book ſhall be bought, in which theſe Orders ſhall be written.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>XIV. <hi>None ſhall be admitted into this Society without the conſent of the Miniſter who preſides over it; and no Apprentice ſhall be capable of being cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen</hi>
               </item>
               <item>XV. <hi>That if any Caſe of Conſcience ariſe, it ſhall be brought before the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>XVI. <hi>If any Member think fit to leave the Society, he ſhall pay five Skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings to the Stock.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>XVII. <hi>The major part of the Society to conclude the reſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>XVIII. <hi>The following Rules are more eſpecially to be commended to the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this Society,</hi> viz. <hi>To love one another: When reviled, not to revile again: To ſpeak evil of no man: To wrong no man: To pray, if poſſible, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven times a day: To keep cloſe to the Church of <hi>England:</hi> To tranſact all things peaceably and gently: To be help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54145:9"/>to each other: To uſe themſelves to holy Thoughts in their coming in and going out: To examine themſelves eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry night: To give every one their due: To obey Superiors both Spiritual and Temporal.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>This is the ſubſtance of what the Doctor directed on this occaſion. I did many years ago lay theſe things before a very great and worthy Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, (who is now living) to whom I thought it was highly ſit that they ſhould be communicated. I adviſed with him upon the whole matter. And the occaſion was this: There was a certain number of Young Men, who were deſirous to make ſuch a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, and to be concluded by theſe Orders. They applied to a Miniſter in <hi>London</hi> to take upon him the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection and Care of them. I was concern'd for that Miniſter, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon laid the whole caſe before that Prelate. He was clearly of opinion that the Young Men were not to be diſcouraged, and that it was beſt to take care of them, and ſecure that zeal which they expreſſed, in the right Channel; he was well contented to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54145:9"/>leave them to the care and manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Upon which encouragement they were admitted. That time in which this Prelate was conſulted, was not over favourable to any kind of Religious Meetings. And yet the Doctor had the hard meaſure to be cenſured very ſeverely, even ſince this happy Revolution, upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. Endeavours were uſed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get an ill opinion of him in the late Archbiſhop, and in others. But upon due Information, the Archbiſhop was intirely ſatisfied, and was a true Friend to the Doctor to the laſt.</p>
            <p>The Doctor had ſo much buſineſs generally upon his hands, that he had hardly time to eat his Meat. He was often ſent for to ſick and dying Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, frequently conſulted by thoſe who were doubtfull and ſcrupulous, and addreſſed to with Caſes of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſometimes with Caſes that were very extraordinary. He was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo beyond all meaſure followed by the Poor and Needy, by them that wanted Money, or wanted his favour to procure them ſome Boon or other. He was extremely prone to do good Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54145:10"/>this was well known, and it fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with him accordingly.</p>
            <p>But in the late Reign his labour was much encreaſed. Great endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours were uſed to introduce Popery, and to delude the poor People. No man was more ſtout and diligent than the Doctor at that time. He preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moſt vigorouſly againſt that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Doctrine, prepared his Auditors againſt the day of trial, and was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared (I doubt not) for Martyrdom himſelf. 'Tis very well known that he declined no labour, ſhunn'd no Conference with the Popiſh Prieſts, omitted not what was in his power to do to ſtemm the Tide. There are thoſe living, of the greateſt figure and character, who very well know the truth of this matter.</p>
            <p>But thanks be to God, the fear of Popery vaniſh'd upon his preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's coming to the Crown. But then the Doctor had another tryal. His Maintenance at the <hi>Savoy</hi> was but ſmall, and in great meaſure precari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. And yet was that all his Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, excepting a Prebend of the Church of <hi>Exeter</hi> of but 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> 
               <hi>per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> without any Corps belonging
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54145:10"/>to it. But it was really much leſs than that, Charges deducted. This was all his Preferment at that time, and for ſome conſiderable time after. He had not any houſe to live in, but what he hired at a conſiderable rate. He had himſelf, a Wife, and four Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to maintain; and his Children ſo far grown, that they required now a more chargeable Maintenance than formerly, His Maintenance was very little. Thoſe who formerly contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted withdrew their kindneſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſubmitted to the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. He loſt very conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly that way. This I had from his own Mouth. But yet I cannot ſay he complained of it. I confeſs I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard him complain but once, and that was a little before his laſt Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and then he complained that he wanted Money to give to the Poor. The Poor did in great numbers reſort to him at that time; he gave of his own little a very great proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and perhaps ſomething more than might ſeem conſiſtent with what was owing to his own Family. But he had a generous Soul, and knew not how to deny him that asked. The
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54145:11"/>words of our Saviour, <hi>Give to every one that asketh thee,</hi> made a great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon his Mind: I found up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on diſcourſe with him, that he was ſo very much under the power of thoſe words, that he thought he could hardly be at liberty even from a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Beggar: And ſometime I have taken occaſion to diſcourſe him on that ſubject; but I ſhall not trouble the Reader with any thing farther in that matter.</p>
            <p>In theſe mean circumſtances he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued for ſeveral years after the late Revolution. But he went on in his labours, and chearfully purſued the great end of his Miniſtry, and the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for which he was ſent into the World. It pleaſed God to raiſe up a friend who concerned himſelf on his behalf. It was the Lord Admiral <hi>Ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel,</hi> now the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Orford.</hi> He, before he went to Sea, went to the Queen to take leave of her Majeſty, and when he was with her, begged of her that ſhe would be pleaſed to beſtow ſome Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment on Dr. <hi>Horneck.</hi> The Queen told him that ſhe could not at preſent think of any way of preferring the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54145:11"/>Doctor, and with this anſwer the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral was diſmiſſed. Sometime after this, the Queen told what had paſſed on this occaſion to the late Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. She added withal, that ſhe was concerned, leſt the Admiral ſhould think her too unconcerned on the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor's behalf, and adviſed with him what was to be done for the Doctor's advantage, and ſatisfaction of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral. The Archbiſhop adviſed the Queen to promiſe him the next Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bend of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> that ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to become void. This the Queen did, and lived to make her word good in the year 1693. The late Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop upon notice that the Prebend was void, introduced the Doctor to the Queen, and he was made Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendary of that Church. I had this relation from the late Archbiſhop. And I mention that noble Lord, who ſpake to the Queen on the Doctor's behalf, with all the honour imaginable. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that noble Family, the Duke of <hi>Bedford,</hi> and his noble Relatives, had a great kindneſs for the Doctor, and it ought not to be forgotten in this place. I have often heard the Doctor mention them with reſpect.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:54145:12"/>
            <p>He was now in eaſier circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and provided of an Houſe, and at a ſmall diſtance from his People, of whom he took the very ſame care which he did before. He preached very conſtantly among them, and diſcharged other Miniſterial duties as before! He kept in his hands ſome part of the Houſe he formerly lived in, and was conſtantly there a day or two in a Week, (beſides his other occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal times) on purpoſe to attend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe poor, and afflicted, and ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous People that reſorted thither for help and advice. He did very often ſtay all night in that place, that he might be in a readineſs to aſſiſt thoſe that expected him there.</p>
            <p>His Prebend of <hi>Exeter</hi> lying at a great diſtance from him, he expreſſed an inclination to reſign it, and he did ſo the next year. The preſent Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells</hi> had a ſmall Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bend which that year became void, little better as to the annual Rent than that of <hi>Exeter,</hi> but then it had a Corps of ſome value, and two lives were gone. It required no Reſidence, and if it had, it was much nearer to him than <hi>Exeter.</hi> The Biſhop made him
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54145:12"/>an offer of it, hoping that he might receive ſome Fine for the better ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of his Family. He was admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to it upon <hi>Sept.</hi> 28. 1694. He enjoyed it to the day of his death, but I fear he made no advantage of it, his charges conſidered; or if he did, it was very ſmall. He was offered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a Fine, and (conſidering his ſmall income) a conſiderable Summ, but yet not above one half of the real value. 'Twas ſuppoſed, I preſume, that he would have greedily laid hold of the preſent advantage and gain, (as too many have done) without conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering what was decent and becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, with reſpect to the Church and to his Succeſſor. But they that thought ſo were deceived in their Man. He generouſly refuſed the offer, and left the Lives to be filled up by his Succeſſor. But it having a Vicarage annexed in his gift, he went and preached to the People, and gave out good Rules in his Viſitation, for the good of the Souls in the Peculiar un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Juriſdiction. In this Journey of his, he happened to meet with the Leſſee of the Corps, from whom alone he might expect a Fine. Inſtead of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54145:13"/>minding his own gain, and addreſſing to the Leſſee with art and complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance, in order to make a worldly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, he plainly reproved the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee of Immorality; which others were prone enough to ſpread abroad, but perhaps no other had the courage to reprove. He choſe rather to loſe his Fine (as he did) than omit his Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>Upon this occaſion I cannot but add, that he had in great meaſure the Spirit and Courage of <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt.</hi> He durſt reprove a great Man; and perhaps that man lived not that was more conſcientious in this matter. I very well knew a great Man, and Peer of the Realm, from whom he had juſt expectations of Preferment; but this was ſo far from ſtopping his Mouth, that he reproved him to his Face; and that too in a matter that few men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides would have adventured on. He miſſed of his <hi>Preferment</hi> indeed, but <hi>ſaved his own Soul.</hi> He could not fawn or flatter, cringe and comply, for his own gain and worldly advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
            <p>Upon this conſideration, his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance and Friendſhip were very
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54145:13"/>deſirable by every good man, that would be better. He would in him be very ſure of a Friend that would <hi>not ſuffer ſin upon him.</hi> I may ſay of him what <hi>Pliny</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Plin. l. <hi>1.</hi> ep. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> ſays of <hi>Corellius Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus,</hi> whoſe death he laments, <hi>amiſi vitae meae teſtem,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I have loſt a</hi> faithfull <hi>witneſs of my Life;</hi> and may add, what he ſaid upon that occaſion to his Friend <hi>Calviſius, Vereor ne neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentiùs vivam,</hi> i. e. <hi>I am afraid</hi> (ſays he) <hi>leſt for the time to come I ſhould live more careleſly.</hi> Certain I am, that his Friends and Familiars have a great loſs upon this account. They have loſt a great Pattern of Vertue, and a very faithfull Monitor and Reprover of Vice and Folly.</p>
            <p>A faithfull Reprover is a very great help in our Chriſtian Courſe. He is to be valued above the greateſt trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. <hi>He that would be ſafe</hi> (ſays one of the Ancients) <hi>muſt have a faithfull Friend, or a bitter Enemy,</hi> that he may fly from Vice by the Monitions of the one, or Invectives of the other. We need one of theſe to ſet us right. We read that the Grandees of <hi>Japan</hi> do each of them maintain in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral houſes one or two perſons, whoſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54145:14"/>office and buſineſs is to obſerve the actions of their Maſters, und freely to admoniſh them when they do any thing <hi>imprudently</hi> or <hi>wickedly</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Varen. <hi>deſcripe.</hi> Japon.</note> 'Tis worthy of our imitation, and highly expedient. Great men are followed and corrupted by Flatterers; they have but few Friends who have Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Honeſly enough to tell them of their faults.</p>
            <p>But this may be thought too great a Digreſſion; I therefore return to give a farther account of this excellent Man. He was now in better circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances as to the world, than he had been, but not leſs diligent and labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. He went on in his Maſter's work with moſt unwearied labour, and ſpent his whole time and ſtrength in it. And it was his delight and his choice. Indeed thoſe who were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him thought he did more than he was able long to bear. He grew ſoon after this very infirm and ſickly. He fell into dangerous ſits of the Stone<note n="†" place="margin">The learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed W <hi>Sch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> us'd to call this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, to which he himſelf was much ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t, <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dioſorum ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llum.</hi>
               </note>, made very little, and that a bloody Water. He walked with difficulty, and could hardly bear a Coach. I have often told him, that he could not long continue under the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54145:14"/>labour which he underwent; and I plainly ſaw that he declined, and would do ſo more and more, unleſs he did remit his very great labours. I convinc'd him abundantly of the truth of what I obſerved of him. He was ſenſible of it, and ſeem'd very incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to retire from the multiplicity of buſineſs with which he was almoſt overwhelm'd. He went on in his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed labours to <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> 1696. Then his work increaſed upon him, and whereas other men's labours are then intermitted, his were augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For at that time he had more frequent Communions, beſides an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible number of Applications from poor People, who then expect relief and aſſiſtance; which gave him great diverſion and trouble. He neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs went through all this labour and trouble, with as great chearſulneſs as was poſſible But not long after I found a plain alteration in him for the worſe. On the 23d of <hi>January</hi> I was much concern'd for him. He was to preach the next day at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and I was of opinion that it was not ſafe for him to do it. I was very earneſt with him to ſpare himſelf that day,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54145:15"/>but could not prevail. He preached there, and it was the laſt Sermon that he preached. In the Evening I found him (to my great ſorrow) in great diſorder. From that time his illneſs encreaſed upon him. His Urine up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the matter totally ſtopped; he was in pain, and greatly indiſpoſed all that Week. And yet when I usk'd him (which I frequently did) if he were not in great pain, all the anſwer that I could get from him was, that <hi>the pain he felt was tolerable.</hi> There was nothing wanting that could be thought of towards giving him eaſe. The a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt Phyſicians were conſulted, and they conſulted and adviſed upon his caſe, and attended him with great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and tenderneſs, but without ſucceſs. On Sunday Morning, <hi>Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary</hi> 31ſt, he was worſe than ever he had been, inſomuch that thoſe about him thought him dying about eleven in the Morning. I was then at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter-Abbey,</hi> and was ſent for out of the Church to pray with him. I found him very ſenſible. I asked him, if he were ſenſible that he was dying, he replied that he was. I asked him if he were alſo reſigned, and willing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54145:15"/>to die, he replied very readily, that he was willing to die. I asked him if he had conſidered the words, <hi>Heb.</hi> II. 14, 15; and whether or not he found himſelf delivered from all the ſlaviſh <hi>fear of death,</hi> he replied very quick, looking up to Heaven, that he was delivered from that fear. He was in an excellent frame, and joyned with the Prayers which the Church appoints on ſuch occaſions, with great expreſſions of Devotion. Sometime after this, I found him delirous, and not long after ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs. After ſome few hours Groans he expired, <hi>viz.</hi> at Eight a Clock that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening, being then about the 56th year of his Age<note n="*">Before this laſt I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>huſs, of which he died, he fell (in the year <hi>1678</hi>) into along and languiſhing Sickneſs, occaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed through his indefatigable Application to the Duties and Funllions of his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. It brought him well nigh to his Grave The good Man aſcribed his Recovery, under God, to the tender Care of his veritutus Wife, with whom he always liv'd in great Courn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed and Union, and to the Prayers of pious People put up to Heaven on his behalf; as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from ſome devent Meditations which the compos'd on that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and which have been found ſince his De. caſe among his Papers. In Thankſgiving to God for his Preſervation at that time, which he himſelf look'd on as next to miratulous, he kept a Day Monthly in his Family ever after, and preach'd yearly a Commemoration. Sermon to his beloved Congregation at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> wherein he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed God's Mercies to him, and excited others to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and truſt in him in the like Extremities. He alſo diſtribute a la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly to the Peer upon that Day. This was his conſtant Method, to treaſure up God's Previdences to him, and to ſanctifie and improve them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> only to his own Uſe, but to the Uſe and Benefit of others.</note>.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:54145:16"/>
            <p>His Body was opened, and it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared quickly what was the cauſe of his Death. Both his Ureters were ſtopped: One of them was ſtopped as a Bottle with a Cork, with a Stone that entered the top of the Ureter with a ſharp end, the upper part of which was thick and much too big to enter any farther: The other was ſtopped alſo with Stones, of much leſs firmneſs and conſiſtence than the other.</p>
            <p>His Body was interred on <hi>Feb.</hi> 4. in the Abbey Church of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> with great Solemnity, and a vaſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Attendants. Several of the Lords the Biſhops, very many of the moſt eminent Clergy about the City, and an incredible number of other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, were preſent on that occaſion. And it muſt be ſaid that the Church of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> ſhewed the great kindneſs they had for him, by the great care they took of his very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and ſolemn Interment.</p>
            <p>Before I proceed any farther, I ſhall reflect upon his undaunted Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage when Death look'd him in the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54145:16"/>face. 'Tis certain that there were a great many conſiderations that might have diſpoſed him to deſire; a longer life at that time. I well knew his cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and thoſe of his Family, and how deſirable his life was upon many accounts. But yet this pious man was not only willing to die, but was entirely delivered from the fear of it, and did with great chearfulneſs and alacrity receive the tidings and ſentence of Death.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Hierom</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Hieron. vit. Hila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion.</note> tells that <hi>Hilarion,</hi> juſt when he was expiring, ſpake theſe words, <hi>Egredere, quid times? Egredere anima mea, quid dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas? Septuaginta propè annis ſerviſti Chriſto, &amp; mortem times?</hi> i. e. <hi>Go out, O my Soul, why doſt thou fear? Why doſt thou doubt? Thou haſt ſerved Chriſt near ſeventy years, and art thou afraid to dye?</hi> There was, it ſeems, ſome fear and ſome doubt in <hi>Hilarion.</hi> This Servant of God was, by his Grace, delivered intirely from all ſuch fear or doubt. I ſay, by the Grace of God he was delivered, and ſpecial Grace it was. Very good Perſons, when they come to die, have their doubts, and their great ſears too. It
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54145:17"/>is an eaſie thing to diſcourſe wiſely and Philoſophically of the Contempt of Death; but they which do ſo, have not the ſame Preſence of Mind when Death looks them in the face. We have a famous ſtory to this purpoſe, concerning the Father of <hi>Clinias,</hi> who was wont to deſpiſe Death in his Health, and was in great dread of it when it drew near to him, as <hi>Plato</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates it<note n="*" place="margin">Platon. Axiochus.</note>.</p>
            <p>It muſt be confeſſed, that this good Man had taken the right courſe to be freed from the fear of Death, by lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a very painfull and laborious, a very uſefull and charitable, a very devout and pious Life.</p>
            <p>His Life was very painfull and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious. Few men ever took the Pains which he did. He was mortified to all worldly Pleaſures, and ſenſual Satisfactions, and uſed himſelf to great Labours and moſt exemplary Diligence. There is nothing renders us more afraid to die, than a ſoft and voluptuous Life. <hi>Oh Death, how bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is the remembrance of thee to a man that liveth in reſt in his poſſeſſions? Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clus.</hi> XLI. 1. We have an example of this in <hi>Agag.</hi> He came delicately,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:54145:17"/>and was <hi>pinguiſſimus &amp; tremens</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Vulg. lat. in locum.</note>, i.e. <hi>very fat and trembling;</hi> and no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then that he ſhould complain of <hi>the bitterneſs of death:</hi> For ſo certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he does, however our Interpreters come to render his words. Death muſt be bitter where voluptuouſneſs makes life ſweet.</p>
            <p>His Life was alſo very uſefull and very charitable. Multitudes they were that received relief and advantage by him. And there is a particular pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to ſuch men, that God will <hi>ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then them upon the bed of languiſhing,</hi> and <hi>make their bed in their ſickneſs,</hi> Pſal. XLI. 3. Our Saviour wou'd have his followers pray, that their <hi>flight</hi> might not be in the <hi>Winter,</hi> or on the <hi>Sabbath.</hi> One of the Fathers<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Theophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lact.</hi> on <hi>Matth.</hi> 84.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodates the words to my preſent purpoſe. <q>Happy is that man that does not, when he leaves this World, lead an <hi>unfruitfull</hi> life, nor yet an <hi>idle</hi> one. The Winter is the <hi>barren</hi> time of the year, and the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was a time, not of Labour, but of Reſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>His Life was alſo very devour and pious, of which more afterward. I mention only in this place, his very
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54145:18"/>devout and frequent receiving the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Communion, which is a great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative to a comfortable Death. I will repeat the Doctor's own Words, which many years ago fell from him to his hearers at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and which were verified in him many years after. <hi>A worthy receiving of the Lord's Supper</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is the beſt preparative for death.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cruciſic. Jeſus, p. 557.</note> 
               <hi>No man can die uncomfortably, that makes it his buſineſs, as often as be comes to this Table, to receive wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily. Death cannot hurt him,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for by his worthy receiving he hath laid up a good foundation for the time to come,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now more particularly give the Character of this excellent Perſon, and the kindneſs I had for him ſhall not prevail with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne to exceed in his commendation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall begin with his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Piety towards God, of which he was a very conſpicuous Example. His Religion had its full power and fore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon him, it transform'd him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the image and likeneſs of God. It hath always been eſteemed ſafe advice, <hi>imitare cum quom tolimus,</hi> i. e. <hi>to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate him whom we worſhip.</hi> On this
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:54145:18"/>account ſome of the Heathens excuſed their vices, becauſe their Poets, and men of the Stage, repreſented their Gods as having practiſed the ſame things. He worſhipped the true and living God, the holy and mercifull, the God of truth and righteouſneſs, and not only the greateſt and moſt powerfull, but the beſt of Beings. He was a follower of God, and his Divine Image was fairly ſtamped and impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon his Soul. He imitated God in thoſe two things which one of the Ancients tells us will make us like God, <hi>viz. ſpeaking truth, and beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing benefits.</hi> A man of greater ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and veracity I never knew; and there are multitudes that will witneſs that <hi>he went about doing good.</hi> He did vow in his Baptiſm to renounce the Devil, the World, and Fleſh. Some men go no farther. All their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on comes from the Font. This good Man perform'd his Vow, he caſt out of himſelf the Evil One, and renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced all his Works, overcame the World in the nobleſt ſenſe, and ſubdued and mortified all the ſinfull deſires of the fleſh. He was a Conquerour, and <hi>more than Conquerour.</hi> He devoted himſelf
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54145:19"/>intirely, and without reſervation, to the ſervice of his God. It was not only his buſineſs, but his choice and delight, his meat and drink. I need not ſay that he was much in Prayers and Faſtings, in Meditation and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Diſcourſe, very frequent in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Communions, in reading and hearing the Word, in watchings and great auſterities. He wiſely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that theſe were the <hi>means,</hi> and not the <hi>end</hi> of Religion; that theſe are not <hi>godlineſs,</hi> but only <hi>helps,</hi> and the <hi>way</hi> to it. He arrived at the <hi>end</hi> of theſe things. He had an ardent love of God, a great Faith in him, and was reſigned to his Will: He had an unſpeakable Zeal for his Honour, a profound regard to his Word, and to his Worſhip, and to all that had the neareſt relation to him, or did moſt partake of his image and likeneſs. He was a Man after God's own heart. He lived under a moſt gratefull ſenſe of his Mercies, he was governed by his fear, and had a lively ſenſe of God's ſpecial Care and Providence. He had that ſenſe of God's Mercy in giving us his Son to die for us, that it was obſerved of him, that when he diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:54145:19"/>of that Argument, he uſed no meaſure, no bounds, or limits of his Diſcourſe. His heart was ſo affected with that Argument, that he cou'd not put a ſtop to himſelf. <hi>Jeſus</hi> was his Lord and Maſter, and he had his Life and Example always before him, and conformed himſelf to it in the whole Tenour and Courſe of his Life. His Religion was unaffected and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial, it was genuine and primitive, and ſo great a pattern he was, that he might have paſſed for a Saint, even in the firſt and beſt times of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            <p>He was of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and a moſt true Son of that Church, and gave the greateſt proofs of it. Far was he from the Innovations of the <hi>Roman Church</hi> on the one hand, and from Enthuſiaſm on the other. His Writings are a ſufficient proof of this. I very well know that when the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath been traduced and diſparaged, he hath not forborn to make ſo vigorous a Defence, that he loſt a very great Man's friendſhip by it, and felt the Effects of it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards by the loſs of a conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able worldly advantage, which he
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:54145:20"/>would otherwiſe have flood very fair for. He ſhewed his Zeal for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> when ſhe was in greateſt danger from many Enemies, eſpecially from the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> At that time, when ſome were ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked as to change their profeſſion, and others ſo tame as to ſit ſtill, and not to concern themſelves when the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were at the Gates; (for there were too many, that profeſſed to be Sons of this Church, and do ſo ſtill, who were over-awed, and durſt not appear with that Courage which God and all good Men might juſtly have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from them) then did this good Man beſtir himſelf, and <hi>lifted up his Voice like a Trumpet,</hi> and undaunted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defended the Church, when ſhe moſt needed it. God be praiſed there were others who did ſo likewiſe, with great vigour and reſolution, and great hazard of their liberty and worldly Comforts. And many of theſe had the hard hap to be traduced by their lukewarm Brethren, who cry up the Church, as if theſe were not the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine Sons of this Church. It hath not been for the advantage of the Church, that thoſe Men have been
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:54145:20"/>decried as not genuine Church-men, who have done her the greateſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; on the other hand, ſome vaunt themſelves to be ſuch, who have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been any ſupport to their Mother in her greateſt diſtreſs. There are ſome of theſe who are like the Images we ſee in many Churches, that are ſo placed in that bending Poſture, as if they bore upon their Shoulders the weight of the Building, whereas in truth they are only the fancy of the Architect, and bear no weight at all. The Doctor believed the Doctrine of this Church, obeyed her Injunctions, and conformed to her Conſtitutions: He admoniſhed and diligently inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Charge, kept Multitudes in her Communion, and lived up to her ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Rules, and was ready to ſacrifice all that was dear to him in the World to promote the true Intereſt of this Church. He would not indeed take the Cure of Souls, and then put them out to nurſe to ſome cheap and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Curate; receive the <hi>profits,</hi> and leave another man to take the <hi>pains:</hi> He would not take a <hi>Vicarage,</hi> and <hi>ſwear</hi> reſidence before his Ordinary, and afterwards refuſe to <hi>reſide,</hi> on pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:54145:21"/>of ſome privilege or exempt Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as very many have done. But a Church-man he was not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding. Indeed the beſt of men have been miſ-repreſented. And there are a Number of the moſt uſeleſs men, that yet in all places are crying up the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle regard to her holy Rules. I knew two men of the ſame Faculty, in the ſame neighbourhood. They were in their profeſſion very eminent. One of theſe had the Name of a Church of <hi>England</hi> man, the other of a Fanatick. And yet it is well known that the firſt very rarely (if at all) came to the Church or Communion, the other was a great frequenter of both.</p>
            <p>The Doctor was a man of very good Learning. He had very good skill in Languages. He had addicted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the <hi>Arabic</hi> from his younger time; and retained it in good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to the laſt. He had great skill in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> likewiſe, nor was his skill limited to the <hi>Biblical Hebrew</hi> only, (in which he was a great Maſter) but he was ſeen in the <hi>Rabbinical</hi> alſo. He was a moſt diligent Reader of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures in that Language in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:54145:21"/>which they were originally written. <hi>Sacras literas tractavit indefeſſo ſtudio.</hi> This Dr. <hi>Spanheim</hi> ſays of him in his youth; <hi>viz. that he was indefatigable in the Study of the Holy Scriptures.</hi> He adds that he was then one of an <hi>elevated wit, of a mind that was cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and covetous of making ſubſtantial proficiency:</hi> And alſo that he gave a Specimen of it about the year 1659, (when he was very young) by a publick defending a Diſſertation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Vow of <hi>Jephtah,</hi> touching the ſacrificing his Daughter. This upon his own requeſt and motion he publickly defended with great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of mind. He had very good skill in Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſial Divinity, and Caſuiſtical al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. Perhaps few men in his time were more frequently applied to with Caſes of Conſcience than the Doctor was. As he had vaſt numbers of theſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, ſo many times the Caſes were very rare, and ſurprizing, and ſuch as are but very ſeldom to be met with. He would often relate the Caſe to me, and tell me what his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion was, and how he delivered it. I do ſolemnly declare that I never heard
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:54145:22"/>him deliver his opinion, but I was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely ſatisfied with it. And I did think him as valuable for this skill, as for any other whatſoever. He was a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſtant Preacher. He was very affectionate and lively in his Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, plain and pathetical; he ſpake from his own, and pierced the hearts of his hearers. I will not in this place ſpeak of his Writings, I may have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to mention them afterwards. I ſhall only ſay here, that there is a great ſtrain of Piety and Devotion in them, and they are very inſtructive to the well-diſpoſed Readers. He had great correſpondencies with learned Men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, and was often viſited by them, and this preſerved in him that readineſs which he had in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Latin Tongue with conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eaſe and freedom.</p>
            <p>As for his Paſtoral care and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, he was a great Example. He was a pattern to thoſe of the Holy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, whom they might ſecurely follow. He well underſtood not only the <hi>Dignity,</hi> but the <hi>Duty</hi> and Charge of his Holy Function. He had a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſenſe of the worth of Souls, and of the great care that is to be had of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:54145:22"/>them. Hence it proceeded that he was ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconcilable to <hi>Pluralities,</hi> and <hi>Non-reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence;</hi> Hence it was that he laboured indefatigably Night and Day: Hence it was that he was ſo very painfull a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, ſo very hard a Student: Hence it was that he was ſo very diligent in Catechizing the youth, in viſiting the ſick, and in all the parts of his holy Office. His heart was wholly ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on gaining Souls to God. In this work he labour'd inceſſantly. And thoſe who were thus diſpoſed among the Clergy, he honoured greatly, and ſerved them to his power. A conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable number of ſuch Miniſters were well known to him, and ſome among them that were not well provided for. Theſe, upon occaſion, he recommended to Cures and Imployments, as he had opportunity offered him from Perſons of Quality, who did many times ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to the Doctor on theſe occaſions. And happy were they who took this courſe, they might ſecurely reſt upon his Recommendation. No man was ever more faithfull in this truſt; I know not but I may ſay, no man was more happy than the Doctor in this matter. I have tried him ſeveral times,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:54145:23"/>and was not deceived. Had I been Patron of many Livings, I could ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely have relied upon his Wiſdom and Fidelity in diſpoſing them all. He went by a true meaſure. He looked on a Living (as we call it) as a <hi>Cure,</hi> rather than a <hi>Benefice.</hi> He valued the <hi>Flock</hi> more than the <hi>Fleece,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently preferred thoſe who did the ſame. On this very account, the Death of the Doctor was a loſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable; and I reckon my ſelf a very great loſer upon this account. When he was alive, if I wanted a Pariſh-Miniſter, a Curate, a Maſter of a School, or Chaplain, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I was ſecure, that by him I might be well ſupplied. His Recommendation weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more with me than many Hands, than Seals, and ample Forms and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonials from great Names and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties of Men. I well knew that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could bribe him to commend that Perſon to a place of truſt, whom he did not know to be fit for it. I heartily wiſh his Example in this were followed. Nor do I think that what I ſaid laſt is any Digreſſion, when I ſpeak of his Paſtoral care. For his care in recommending thoſe only
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:54145:23"/>whom he knew to be fit, was an effect of it. It cannot be that he who will commend any perſon to holy Orders, or the cure of Souls, ſhould have a due ſenſe of the Paſtoral care. And I heartily wiſh that the Clergy would be very cautious whom they recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend for Orders, or for Inſtitution; and that College-Teſtimonials were given with greater care than they have been.</p>
            <p>I add, that he had a very great zeal for <hi>Reformation.</hi> This will be no Commendation of him to the luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm, and formal Chriſtians: Nay it will render him leſs in the eyes of ſome men, who mightily cry up the Church. And therefore I muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain my ſelf in this matter, leſt I be miſ-underſtood, and the Memory of the Doctor ſuffer upon this account.</p>
            <p>When I ſay that he was zealous for <hi>Reformation,</hi> I do not mean that he was for reforming or altering the Laws. For though he did not think the Laws <hi>immutable,</hi> yet did he not plead for the changing them. He was well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in the Laws of Church and State, and was not for Innovations. He was no Enemy to the Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:54145:24"/>
            <p>The <hi>Reformation</hi> which he was for, was ſuch a one as might be conſiſtent with the Law, and indeed was the end of the Law it ſelf. He was very much for a Reformation <hi>uſquè ad le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem;</hi> and it will be very ſtrange that any conſidering Man ſhould be againſt ſuch a Reformation as this; 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that he that is ſo, is againſt the Law at the ſame time. He was for Reformation of <hi>Manners,</hi> and a ſtrict regard to the Diſcipline and holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the Church. He lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Profaneneſs and Diſorders which had broken in among us, and threatned our Ruin. He endeavoured to keep up the Life and Spirit of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and perhaps, conſidering his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Capacity, he did as much this way as any man that lived in his time. He never needed any Diſpenſation himſelf, and could not without great grief of heart, ſee the beſt Laws tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled upon by worldly and ungodly Men, or defeated and eluded by the craft and artifices of others. I need make no apology for him, that he was againſt Non reſidence and Pluralities, that he was for frequent Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and for a ſtrict care in Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:54145:24"/>the Youth. All this is agreeable to the Senſe of our Church. And his great Zeal againſt all profaneneſs and immorality cannot be blamed, becauſe he was <hi>zealouſly affected in a good mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For his Juſtice to all mankind, he was a great pattern. He gave all men their <hi>due,</hi> in the greateſt latitude of that word. He did not only pay his debts, and diſcharge his truſt, but paid all due honour and reſpect to worth and vertue, where-ever he ſound it. Nothing could render him partial. No friendſhip, no power, no intereſt whatever could turn him aſide, or ſo much as ſet a falſe <hi>biaſs</hi> upon him.</p>
            <p>His Charity was Divine, and a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty imitation of the love of God and of Chriſt. He ſought not his own, but with great induſtry purſued the good of others. There are multitudes alive that have received great rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t and comfort from him He did not ſpend his time in court and careſs, in viſiting great Perſons, and hunting after Preferment or Applauſe. <hi>He went about doing good.</hi> And in this he was indefatigable. His heart was ſet upon it, and this made him deſpiſe the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:54145:25"/>difficulty which lay in his way. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he went, this was his buſineſs and deſign. His Charity was large, and diffuſive. It extended to the Bodies, the Eſtates, and Souls of Men. He ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d and taught; He inſtructed and comforted, and relieved thoſe who wanted help. I cannot but apply to him what <hi>Libanius Sophiſta</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Socrat.</hi> Apolog.</note> ſaid of <hi>Socrates,</hi> in his Apology for him. Thus he pleads for him to the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> his Citizens. <hi>Ye men of</hi> Athens, (ſays he in his Declamation) <hi>ſave and preſerve</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i. e. <hi>a ſincere Friend, a kind Man, a good Counſellor, a righteous Citizen! He could not lead an Army, but he knew how to reprove,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Your laws and ſuffrages are of great value, and</hi> Socrates <hi>is of no ſmall price, who watcheth thoſe who tranſgreſs, reproves the injurious, that diſchargeth this publick Office for the City. How many, think ye, that once neglected to educate their Children, by his means took that care upon them? How many that quarrelled with their brethren, did he reclaim? How many that abuſed their parents, did he bring to do them reverence? They feared the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:54145:25"/>reproofs of</hi> Socrates <hi>more than the Courts of Juſtice. They knew they could buy off an Accuſer there; but they that did amiſs could not eſcape his reproofs, nor bribe him to be ſilent.</hi> So it was; this holy Man was a great Bleſſing to the Publick, and more eſpecially to the City, where he reproved the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors, encouraged the vertuous, directed the ſcrupulous, and relieved the indigent. <hi>Libanius</hi> goes on, and repreſents what Strangers and Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners would ſay when <hi>Socrates</hi> was dead, and what Diſcourſes they ſhould be entertained with, who ſhould come to <hi>Athens</hi> to ſee the <hi>man,</hi> and coming too late for that, ſhou'd viſit his Tomb. <hi>One,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſhall ſay to another, point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the place, Here he diſcourſed of Fortitude, and there of Sobriety, and in yonder place of Juſtice: Here is the place, where he run down</hi> Prodicus; <hi>and there, where he was too hard for</hi> Prota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras: <hi>In another, he overcame</hi> Eleius, <hi>and</hi> Leontinus. I am very ſure it may be ſaid of this holy Man, The places may be ſhewn where he was doing good; where he taught, and where he relieved; where he entred the liſts with Papiſts, and where, with the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:54145:26"/>other Enemies of the Church, where he inſtructed the Youth, and where he encouraged and directed the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Chriſtians, and where he exhorted the elder. There are thoſe who can point to the places, and truly ſay: Here is the Family whom he relieved, and here live the poor Widows whom he provided for; Here is the place where he preached, and where he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded his Auditors to frequent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and brought vaſt Multitudes of Men and Women to conſtant Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on that holy Ordinance! The truth is, if the particulars were enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, (I ſay the particulars of his Charity) they alone would make a Volume.</p>
            <p>One piece of Charity deſerves to be remembred to his honour, and that was his telling Men of their faults, not only publickly, but privately too. His reproofs may well be reckoned among his Charities. I may truly ſay of him, as <hi>Libanius</hi> does of <hi>Socrates,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i. e. <hi>He made thoſe better whom he did bite.</hi> He bit and healed at once. There was no gall, no venom in him. It all proceeded from unfeigned Charity to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:54145:26"/>the Souls of Men. He could not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſin upon his Brother. He had the zeal of <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> and durſt and did admoniſh, and reprove the greateſt. Of which matter I could ſay more than I think is convenient for me to be particular in. In truth he had the Spirit of the Ancient Prophets, and of the Holy Conſeſſours of the Primitive Church. A Man that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed with him much, wou'd be ſure to hear of it if he did amiſs. He was far from ſlander and detraction, from that <hi>lingua tertia,</hi> as it is called among the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> which does three miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs at once, <hi>viz.</hi> to the <hi>ſpeaker,</hi> to the <hi>hearer,</hi> and to the <hi>ſlanderer. There is that ſpeaketh like the piercings of a ſword, but the tongue of the wiſe is health,</hi> Prov. XII. 18. He had the perfect maſtery of this member, and uſed it to the benefit of his Brother. I never knew any Man living that was more ſtout than this good man in reproving Vice, and in appearing for the Truth; never any Man that was farther removed from flattery and dawbing.</p>
            <p>He was a Friend of a thouſand. He made little ſhew, and was ſparing in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:54145:27"/>his profeſſion of kindneſs. But when he had occaſion to ſerve his friend, he was very induſtrious to do it, and did not think much of pains and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour therein. There are multitudes now alive that can atteſt this.</p>
            <p>He was temperate to the greateſt degree, I had almoſt ſaid to a fault. I have often ſcared that, conſidering his great and conſtant labours, he hardly gave himſelf that refreſhment which was fit. He drank very little Wine at any time, and in the latter part of his Life he did upon the matter wholly forbear it. He had <hi>benè mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ventrem,</hi> as <hi>Seneca</hi> phraſeth it, a <hi>Stomach that was well nurtured,</hi> not nice or curious; it received the meaneſt Proviſion contentedly. After the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigue and labour of the day, he would ſup with an Apple or two, with a little Bread, and ſmall Ale or Milk-Water. This he would receive with great thankfulneſs to God, and great chearfulneſs among his Domeſticks. He was very thankfull to God for a Morſel of Bread, and received the meaneſt Proviſion with the greateſt expreſſions of Gratitude. And yet when he entertained his Friends, he
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:54145:27"/>did it liberally. He was always leaſt concerned for himſelf in theſe things. He very much deny'd himſelf, but to others he was liberal and open-hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and rather than the Poor ſhould want Bread, he would faſt himſelf. He led an <hi>Aſcetick</hi> Life, kept under his Body, and with great induſtry ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced in Holineſs, and a Life that was ſpiritual and heavenly.</p>
            <p>For his Contempt of this lower World he hath given ſufficient proof. He deſpiſed both the ſides or appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of it, I mean the Smiles and Frowns of it. It is well known, that when he lived with the Duke of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemarle,</hi> he might very eaſily have made his Fortunes, as we uſually ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it. Had he made his Court, he could not have ſailed. But inſtead of that, he minded his charge, and the duty of his place. He minded the heavenly Kingdom, and the doing good to Souls. He would often ſpeak very contemptibly of Riches, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that the whole deſign of the Chriſtian Doctrine tended to bring contempt upon Wealth and great Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. He was of opinion, that Riches were (as a great man hath it) <hi>impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimenta
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:54145:28"/>virtutis,</hi> i. e. <hi>the impediments of virtue;</hi> and that a man could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver arrive to any great pitch of virtue, but he muſt be <hi>aut pauper, aut pauperi ſmilis,</hi> i. e. <hi>either poor, or like him that is poor,</hi> as <hi>Seneca</hi> hath it.</p>
            <p>He likewiſe deſpiſed the Frowns of the World. He met with ſore afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The loſs of a conſiderable part of his worldly eſtate at once, I reckon the leaſt of them. I do not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that ever I heard him once com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, but have often heard him give ſolemn thanks to God for his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Some of his Friends would ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſpeak their Reſentment before him, becauſe he was not better pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred. But he would never ſide with them; he diverted the diſcourſe, or ſtopt it, by ſaying, <hi>I ſhall never want.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was a moſt humble and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Chriſtian; of great patience and reſignation to the will of God; a moſt mortified man to the World, and to all the Glory and Pageantry of it. He led an innocent and inoffenſive, and a moſt uſefull Life. He ſpent his hours well, and lived many years in a preparation for Death and Judgment.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:54145:28"/>
            <p>One thing muſt not be forgotten, and that was his great Meekneſs under Obloquies and Reproaches, his great exemplarineſs in forgiving Enemies.</p>
            <p>It may perhaps be ſuppoſed that he had no Enemies, and it will eaſily be granted, that he could deſerve none. But they do not know this world, that think innocence and uſefulneſs will protect any man againſt Malice, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, and Ill-will. <hi>Nulla unquam magna gloria ſine magna fuit invidia, Worthy actions will always be followed with En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy.</hi> 'Tis by <hi>Julius Celſus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jul. Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus de vit. J. Caeſaris.</note> reported, that when <hi>Alcibiades</hi> asked counſel of <hi>Socrates,</hi> what courſe he ſhould take to avoid Envy, <hi>Socrates</hi> replied, <hi>vive ut Therſites,</hi> i. e. <hi>live like Therſites.</hi> Had he lived a ſoft and trifling life, he might have avoided it eaſily: But he did his duty with great exactneſs, and that was the occaſion of Envy. The old Monk, that was asked by a young one how he might paſs eaſily and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly through the world, told him, as one rule, that he ſhould <hi>fungi officio taliter qualiter,</hi> i. e. <hi>That he ſhould not be exact in doing his duty,</hi> but <hi>do it</hi> (as we ſay) <hi>ſo, ſo</hi> The Doctor could not live like <hi>Therſites,</hi> he could
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:54145:29"/>not do his Maſters work negligently, and as this drew many followers and admirers after him, ſo it did Envy al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. The truth of the caſe is this. His exemplary Life was a ſtanding reproach upon thoſe who were negligent, and always trudging after Preferment and Wealth. That ſome of the worſt ſhould endeavour to blacken him, hath nothing ſtrange in it at all. This I am very certain of, that the Clergy of the greateſt name, and the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous for Vertue and good Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, had a very great opinion of him.</p>
            <p>He forgave his Enemies, and I could never find him in the leaſt diſturbed on that account.</p>
            <p>He wrote ſeveral Books which he publiſhed; a Catalogue of them will follow the cloſe of theſe Papers. He left alſo many excellent Sermons in MSS. upon the moſt weighty Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; particularly upon our Bleſſed Saviour's Sermon on the Mount, one Volume of which is herewith Printed; the reſt will be ſet forth with all conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient ſpeed; and likewiſe ſeveral others as theſe find encouragement; <hi>viz.</hi> upon the Parable of the Ten Virgins; the Parable of <hi>Dives</hi> and <hi>Lazarus;</hi> ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:54145:29"/>Sacramental Diſcourſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For thoſe which are already publiſhed, they are well known. There is a great vein of Piety and Devotion which runs through them. They ſavour of the primitive Simplicity and Zeal, and are well fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to make men better. They are weak men that are much taken with Flouriſhes and tall Metaphors, with quaint and picquant ſtrokes of wit. His Diſcourſes are all medicinal and healing, and fitted to make the Reader ſerious and devout. That Food is beſt which is nouriſhing, and that Phyſick which cures and reſtores. This good man had no greater aim than to do good.</p>
            <p>I will ſay of him, as <hi>Pliny</hi> did of <hi>Virginius Rufus, Tanti viri mortalitas magis finita eſt quam vita,</hi> i. e. <hi>His Mortality is ended rather than his Life. He lives and will live for ever; and now that he is withdrawn out of our ſight, he will more than ever continue in the Remembrance and Diſcourſes of Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Friends have erected a Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his Memory in the Abbey-Church of <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> The Reverend Mr. <hi>Philip Falle,</hi> a Friend of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, hath added the Inſcriptions fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:54145:30"/>He might have enlarged this excellent Man's Character further, had he not been confined by the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure and Dimenſions of the Table.</p>
            <p>The Inſcription on the Tomb-Stone is as follows.</p>
            <q>Sub hoc Marmore, <lb/>venerandi Sepulchri indice, <lb/>noviſſimum Domini Adventum <lb/>praeſtolantur <lb/>Mortales Exuviae <lb/>
               <hi>ANTONII HORNECK,</hi> 
               <lb/>S. Th. P. <lb/>Caetera, Viator, <lb/>diſce ex vicinâ Tabellâ. <lb/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <lb/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </q>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:54145:30"/>
            <p>The Inſcription on the Monument is this.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Aeternae Memoriae <lb/>
                  <hi>ANTONII HORNECK,</hi> 
                  <lb/>S. Theologiae Profeſſoris<note n="*" place="margin">He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menc'd Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor at <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> in the Year 1681. This is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd here, it having thro' Inadvertency been omitted in its proper place.</note>, <lb/>Regiae Majeſtati à Sacris, <lb/>Hujus Eccleſiae Canonici, <lb/>Viri inter primos docti &amp; eruditi: <lb/>Sed qui potiſſimùm <lb/>Flagrantiſſimo in Deum zelo &amp; religione; <lb/>Vitae Sanctimoniâ; <lb/>Morum gravitate; <lb/>Humanitatis officiis in ſingulos, <lb/>egenos praeſertim &amp; aegrotantes, <lb/>ſedulò impenſis; <lb/>Sacris Concionibus, <lb/>apud. S. <hi>MARIAM LE SAVOY,</hi> 
                  <lb/>per <hi>XXVI</hi> plus minùs annorum curriculum, <lb/>indeſineuter &amp; indefeſſè ad populum habitis; <lb/>Scriptis, <lb/>priſcorum ſaeclorum pietatem, <lb/>&amp; Aſceticam ſeveritatem, <lb/>mirè redolentibus,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:54145:31"/>atque per ora hominum paſſìm volitantibus; <lb/>Longè latèque inclaruit, <lb/>ac ingentem ſibi apud bonos omnes <lb/>famam comparavit.</p>
               <p>Maximis, <lb/>quis in exequendo munere exantlaverat, <lb/>fractus laboribus, <lb/>in Nephritidem incidit; <lb/>lethalique calculo <lb/>viſceribus pertinaciter adhaereſcente, <lb/>candidiſſimam animam coelo reddidit; <lb/>Prid. Calend. Feb. <lb/>Anno Salutis <abbr>
                     <hi>MDCXCVI,</hi>
                  </abbr> 
                  <lb/>Aetatis ſuae <abbr>
                     <hi>LVI.</hi>
                  </abbr> 
                  <lb/>Viro optimo, <lb/>majora merito, <lb/>hoc qualecunque amoris &amp; obſervantiae <lb/>Monimentum, <lb/>Amici, M M. P P.</p>
            </q>
            <closer>α ☧ ω</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:54145:31"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of Books writ by the Reverend Dr. <hi>Anthony Horn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>I. THE Great Law of Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>II. The Beſt Exerciſe, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>III. The Exerciſes of Prayer, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>IV. Delight and Judgment; or a Proſpect of the great Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>V. The Fire of the Altar. Upon the Sacrament, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>VI. The Crucified Jeſus, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>VII. The firſt Fruits of Reaſon.</item>
               <item>VIII. A Letter to a Lady Revolted to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>IX. Queſtions and Anſwers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap>ing the two Religions; <hi>viz.</hi> That
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:54145:32"/>of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and that of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>X. A Poſtſcript to Dr. <hi>Glanvil,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> an Account of Witches in <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>XI. An Anſwer to the Soldiers Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>What ſhall we do?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>XII. Some ſingle Sermons upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Occaſions.</item>
               <item>XIII. Fifteen Sermons upon the fifth Chapter of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> Vol. 1. in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 16. <hi>lin. ult. for</hi> conten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to leave, <hi>r.</hi> contented ſo to leave. <hi>l.</hi> 19. <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>for</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>r.</hi> never, P. 14. <hi>l. penult. for</hi> imitare, <hi>r.</hi> imitari.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:54145:32"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
